<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<RequirementsAnalysis VERSION="0.5.0">
  <Project>
    <name>video2pptx</name>
    <annotation>Automatically extract slide intervals from educational videos, link to SRT/VTT subtitles, enhance with LLM vision analysis, export presentations, manage projects via GUI/CLI, with video player, subtitle overlay, interactive timeline, and smart manual marker snapping.</annotation>
    <keywords>video, slides, markdown, presentation, open-cv, computer-vision, slide-detection, subtitle-alignment, srt, vtt, marp, llm, lm-studio, vision, gui, pyside6, project, timeline, video-player, subtitle-overlay, smart-snap</keywords>
  </Project>

  <Actors>
    <actor-User>Content creator with educational videos and optional SRT/VTT subtitles</actor-User>
  </Actors>

  <UseCases>
    <UC-001>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs video2pptx detect with video + subtitles (all-in-one)</Action>
      <Goal>Get slides.json with slide intervals, representative images, aligned transcript, and optional exports</Goal>
      <Preconditions>Video file exists (.mp4/.mkv/.mov/.webm), subtitles exist (.srt/.vtt)</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>slides.json passes validation, all slides have images, transcript aligned, optional deck.md/deck.pptx generated</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-001</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-001>

    <UC-002>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs video2pptx export-md with slides.json</Action>
      <Goal>Get deck.md — a Marp-formatted Markdown presentation</Goal>
      <Preconditions>slides.json exists and is valid</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>deck.md renders correctly in Marp-compatible viewer</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-002</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-002>

    <UC-003>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Applies --debug flag during detect</Action>
      <Goal>Get debug artifacts: diff_scores.csv, timeline.png, contact_sheet.jpg</Goal>
      <Preconditions>Detection pipeline ran successfully</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Artifacts exist and contain correct data, timeline shows slide changes</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>medium</Priority>
    </UC-003>

    <UC-004>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs video2pptx llm-process with slides.json + slides images</Action>
      <Goal>Get enriched slides.json with LLM-generated slide descriptions and corrected transcript</Goal>
      <Preconditions>slides.json exists with slide images, LM Studio running with vision-capable model</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Each slide has llm_description field with accurate content summary, transcript corrected with slide context terms</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-003</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-004>

    <UC-005>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs video2pptx detect-slides with video only (no subtitles)</Action>
      <Goal>Get slides.json with slide intervals and representative screenshots — no transcript</Goal>
      <Preconditions>Video file exists</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>slides.json with slide intervals and images present. No transcript fields. No errors about missing subtitles.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-005</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-005>

    <UC-006>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs video2pptx notes with slides.json + subtitles</Action>
      <Goal>Get enhanced slides.json with context-aware notes — combines visual slide analysis with subtitle text</Goal>
      <Preconditions>slides.json exists with slide images, subtitles or transcript available</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Notes on each slide reflect both what was said AND what is on the slide. Notes are clean, not raw SRT fragments. Can run multiple times with different subtitles/notes-modes without re-detecting slides.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-004</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-006>

    <UC-007>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs video2pptx roi-tool with a video file</Action>
      <Goal>Get ignore-roi coordinates (x1,y1,x2,y2) by visually selecting a region on the video frame</Goal>
      <Preconditions>Video file exists</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Opens a window showing a frame from the video. User drags a rectangle. Coordinates printed to stdout. Pipes directly into --ignore-roi flag.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>medium</Priority>
    </UC-007>

    <UC-008>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Creates a new project via CLI or GUI</Action>
      <Goal>Get a project.json file that ties together video, subtitles, configs, and pipeline state in one folder</Goal>
      <Preconditions>None</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>project.json is created in the specified output folder. All paths are stored as absolute or project-relative. Project can be reopened later.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-007</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-008>

    <UC-009>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Opens an existing project and runs slide detection via GUI</Action>
      <Goal>Slides are detected without blocking the UI; progress is visible; project state is updated</Goal>
      <Preconditions>Project exists with valid video path; video file exists</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>UI shows progress during detection. After completion, timeline appears with slide intervals. project.json state updated to detect_done=true. project.json slides_json path points to valid output.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-008</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-009>

    <UC-010>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Views detected slides on a timeline and inspects subtitle text per interval</Action>
      <Goal>See entire video as a visual timeline with slide segments; click a segment to see its subtitle text</Goal>
      <Preconditions>Detection completed, slides.json exists with intervals and images</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Timeline shows colored blocks for each slide interval. Clicking a block displays subtitle text for that segment in a side panel. Timecodes are shown.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-009</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-010>

    <UC-011>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Opens Settings dialog and edits LLM system prompt</Action>
      <Goal>View and modify the SYSTEM_PROMPT_REPHRASE that controls how subtitle text is processed by LLM</Goal>
      <Preconditions>Settings dialog is open</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>LLM tab shows the current system prompt in an editable text field. Changes are saved to project config and take effect on next LLM processing. Changes persist across app restarts.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>medium</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-010</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-011>

    <UC-012>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Selects GPU/decoder backend in Settings</Action>
      <Goal>Choose which video decoder backend to use (auto detect, force OpenCV CPU, force PyAV CUDA)</Goal>
      <Preconditions>Settings dialog is open</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Available backends are displayed (detected at startup). User selects one. Selection is saved to project config and used for next detect run. Info about CUDA availability is shown.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>medium</Priority>
    </UC-012>

    <UC-013>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Uses menu bar: File > New/Open/Close/Save Project, Import Video, Import Subtitles, Exit</Action>
      <Goal>Manage project lifecycle and video/subtitle sources via standard desktop menu</Goal>
      <Preconditions>GUI is running</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>File menu contains all listed items. Keyboard shortcuts match platform conventions (Ctrl+N, Ctrl+O, Ctrl+S, Ctrl+Q). Close unloads project and resets UI. Import Video/Subtitles replaces sources in current project. Save writes project.json immediately.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-011</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-013>

    <UC-014>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Opens Project Settings and App Settings from Edit menu</Action>
      <Goal>Configure per-project detection parameters (ROI, thresholds) and app-wide defaults (LLM, GPU, snap_mode)</Goal>
      <Preconditions>GUI is running. Project loaded for Project Settings.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Project Settings: ROI, ignore_rois, threshold, sample_fps, min_slide_duration, dedupe, min_stable_duration. Saved to project.json. App Settings: LLM model/base_url/context, GPU backend, snap_mode, snap_flat_threshold, default paths. Saved to app-config.yaml. New projects inherit app defaults.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-012</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-014>

    <UC-015>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Plays video with subtitle overlay in GUI, controls playback and volume</Action>
      <Goal>Watch video with synced subtitles, seek to specific timestamps, adjust volume</Goal>
      <Preconditions>Video file exists and is accessible. Project loaded. Subtitles present (optional).</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Play/pause/stop buttons work. Time counter shows current/total. Seek slider seeks correctly. Volume slider adjusts audio level. Subtitles appear over video and sync with playback position. If no subtitles, video plays without overlay.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-013</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-015>

    <UC-016>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Views green detected markers on timeline, clicks to open slide image. Adds blue manual markers, which auto-snap to nearest scene boundary</Action>
      <Goal>Navigate detected slides, inspect images, place manual markers that snap to scene changes</Goal>
      <Preconditions>Detection completed (green markers) or not (blue markers only). Slide images exist.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Green markers appear after detection. Double-click opens slide image in system viewer. Right-click adds blue marker. Blue marker snaps to nearest scene change according to snap_mode (diff_only / fallback_analyze / hybrid). Snapped position reflected on timeline.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-014, DF-015</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-016>

    <UC-017>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Chooses analysis quality in Project Settings (fast / detailed experimental / native / custom)</Action>
      <Goal>Control Pass1 analysis frame max side without reducing screenshot or PPTX resolution</Goal>
      <Preconditions>Project open. Dual-resolution detect path available (Phase 19).</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>
        New projects default to fast (analysis_max_side=480).
        Legacy projects missing the field load as native (None).
        UI shows «Качество анализа» without 480p/720p labels.
        Notice states only slide-search is affected; screenshots/PPTX stay full-res.
        Changing quality after Detect requires confirmation and marks detect+downstream stale.
        No-op save does not rewrite revision unnecessarily.
        Detect/Auto use project.detection.analysis_max_side; CLI override still wins when explicit.
      </AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>Phase-20</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-017>
  </UseCases>

  <NonGoals>
    <item-1>No automatic speech recognition (ASR) — subtitles already prepared</item-1>
    <item-2>No OCR text extraction</item-2>
    <item-3>No cloud/remote processing — local only</item-3>
    <item-4>No web UI with user management or multi-user</item-4>
    <item-5>No automatic video download from YouTube/Zoom/Meet</item-5>
    <item-6>No real-time video streaming from network/URL — local files only</item-6>
    <item-7>No real-time slide detection — only batch processing</item-7>
  </NonGoals>

  <Constraints>
    <constraint-1>Must process video without loading entire file into memory (streaming)</constraint-1>
    <constraint-2>Must support Windows, Linux, macOS paths cross-platform</constraint-2>
    <constraint-3>Must support Cyrillic in paths and subtitle text</constraint-3>
    <constraint-4>Must not hard-depend on CUDA — CPU fallback required</constraint-4>
    <constraint-5>Slide detection is deterministic CV — no LLM for change detection</constraint-5>
    <constraint-6>Core processing must not be coupled to UI — CLI works without GUI deps</constraint-6>
    <constraint-7>LLM processing is optional — pipeline works without it</constraint-7>
    <constraint-8>LLM client must support OpenAI-compatible API (LM Studio)</constraint-8>
    <constraint-9>Model must be unloaded after processing to free VRAM</constraint-9>
    <constraint-10>Stage-based pipeline: detect-slides and notes must be independent commands, not one monolithic step</constraint-10>
    <constraint-11>ROI tool must use only built-in OpenCV (no PyQt/Tkinter/Gradio)</constraint-11>
    <constraint-12>Adding subtitles or changing notes-mode must not require re-running slide detection</constraint-12>
    <constraint-13>GUI must be installable as optional extras — `pip install video2pptx[gui]`</constraint-13>
    <constraint-14>GUI must not block during long operations — workers required</constraint-14>
    <constraint-15>Project JSON must be human-readable and hand-editable</constraint-15>
  </Constraints>

  <Risks>
    <risk-1>Low-quality or highly compressed video may cause false positives in slide detection</risk-1>
    <risk-2>Cyrillic subtitle encoding issues on some platforms</risk-2>
    <risk-3>GPU backend may not be available on all systems</risk-3>
    <risk-4>Animations and transitions between slides may cause split or missed segments</risk-4>
    <risk-5>Webcam overlay and UI elements may cause false slide splits</risk-5>
    <risk-6>LM Studio may not be running or model may be unavailable</risk-6>
    <risk-7>Vision LLM may hallucinate slide content details</risk-7>
    <risk-8>Context window may be exceeded for long slide transcripts</risk-8>
    <risk-9>PySide6 adds ~50MB dependency — may conflict with existing Qt installations</risk-9>
    <risk-10>QThread lifecycle bugs may cause crashes on project/worker switching</risk-10>
    <risk-11>QMediaPlayer may not support all video codecs on all platforms — fallback to frame-by-frame display needed</risk-11>
    <risk-12>Subtitle overlay may flicker or desync with rapid seeking</risk-12>
    <risk-13>Smart snap may snap to wrong boundary if diff_scores are noisy or window is too small</risk-13>
  </Risks>

  <OpenQuestions>
    <question-1>Should representative timestamp be configurable or fixed at 80% into segment?</question-1>
    <question-2>Should multiple ignore_rois be specified as repeated --ignore-roi flags or comma-separated?</question-2>
    <question-3>Should GUI support side-by-side comparison of original vs LLM-processed notes?</question-3>
    <question-4>Should timeline support drag-to-reorder slides?</question-4>
    <question-5>Should smart snap window be configurable (seconds before/after marker)?</question-5>
    <question-6>Should subtitle overlay font size/color be configurable in App Settings?</question-6>
  </OpenQuestions>
</RequirementsAnalysis>
